Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
I suppose the president of the shiur שיעור shiur mentioned to me
yesterday about giving a shiur שיעור shiur at 10:30 on Sunday morning.
Would you be interested? Okay, we'll pick up with that in a
minute. Okay, boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, so today's
daf דף daf is ayin chet ע"ח, Ayin Chet, 78, and we
pick up in the middle of ayin zayin amud bet ע"ז עמוד
ב'. Ayin Zayin Amud Bet. Two dots, v'hi b'toch beito והיא בתוך
ביתו, v'hi b'toch beito, we are dealing with the question about the
act of giving of the get גט. get. And as I mentioned,
the mishna משנה mishna talks about giving it directly to the woman
on her body, like in her hand, or in her chatzeira חצרה.
chatzeira. And as I mentioned, the question is, and the question that's
going to be sort of continuing for a while, is to what
degree are we trying to define something which would be a classic
act of kinyan קנין, kinyan, of taking possession of an object? However,
here it can be forced upon her. Or how much is it
just is it a different definition, a physical act of giving? So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara had a whole question about why does it
count to give it into her chatzeira חצרה? chatzeira? Kanta isha kanta
ba'alah קנתה אשה קנתה בעלה. Kanta isha kanta ba'alah. And that could
be framed in two ways: either because since she takes possession of
it, it transfers to the husband. That's a kinyan קנין kinyan model.
Although it seemed that the Gemara's גמרא'ס Gemara's greater concern was: why
is this chatzeir חצר, chatzeir, or the way I certainly understood the
Gemara גמרא, Gemara, why is this chatzeir חצר chatzeir considered part of
her since the husband has rights to the chatzeir חצר? chatzeir? It's
not like her hand. The husband has very, you know, gets the
benefit of it, kinyan peiros קנין
פירות. kinyan peiros. So and that's very different than giving it directly
in her hand herself, where it obviously it is giving it to
her.
And the Gemara's גמרא'ס Gemara's Rava's רבא'ס Rava's at least classic answer,
rather than the special case that he, that he, that he waived
his rights to the kinyan peiros קנין פירות kinyan peiros or he
never got them, Rava's רבא'ס Rava's answer is gita v'yada ba'in k'echad,
gita v'chatzeira ba'in k'echad גיטה וידה באין כאחד גיטה וחצרה באין כאחד,
gita v'yada ba'in k'echad, gita v'chatzeira ba'in k'echad, that we look a
minute into the future and we see that as a result of
get גט get this will be fully her, her chatzeir חצר chatzeir
or her field, so it's considered that as of right now. So
that is enough to make that considered, and that's the chiddush חידוש
chiddush of v'nasan b'yado ונתן בידו, v'nasan b'yado, that even not in
her hand, even in her property, is considered giving it to her.
Okay, so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara continues with that, but we'll
keep in mind those two models of an act of giving as
opposed to, as opposed to the issue of taking possession, a normal
ma'aseh kinyan מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. V'hi b'toch beitah והיא בתוך ביתה.
v'hi b'toch beitah. Now it says, "give it to her and she's
in her house." So the mishna משנה mishna emphasized that she was
actually standing in her house. Why did it emphasize that? Amar Ulla
אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, v'hi she'omedet b'tzad beitah, b'tzad chatzeirah והיא שעומדת
בצד ביתה בצד חצרה, v'hi she'omedet b'tzad beitah, b'tzad chatzeirah, she's physically
on the property itself, like the mishna משנה mishna sounds like. V'Oshaya
omer ואושעיא אמר, v'Oshaya omer, afilu shehi b'Tveria v'chatzeirah b'Tzipori, hi b'Tzipori
v'chatzeirah b'Tveria אפילו שהיא בטבריה וחצרה בציפורי היא בציפורי וחצרה בטבריה, afilu
shehi b'Tveria v'chatzeirah b'Tzipori, hi b'Tzipori v'chatzeirah b'Tveria, no, she could be
in a different city, it doesn't
matter. M'goreshet מגורשת, M'goreshet, it works. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says:
okay, maybe we can get to the svara סברא svara about that
in a minute, but what do you do with the mishna משנה?
mishna? V'ha v'hi b'toch beitah b'toch chatzeirah k'tani והא והיא בתוך ביתה
בתוך חצרה קתני, v'ha v'hi b'toch beitah b'toch chatzeirah k'tani, the mishna
משנה mishna says she's in her yard, in her house? So the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says: hachi ka'amar
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, v'hi k'mi sheb'toch beitah, v'hi k'mi sheb'toch chatzeirah
והיא כמי שבתוך ביתה והיא כמי שבתוך חצרה. v'hi k'mi sheb'toch beitah,
v'hi k'mi sheb'toch chatzeirah. Wherever she is, it's like she's in her
yard, it's like she's in her house. Which is very strange. Why
are you telling me that? Why would I have thought you needed
it to be in the house that you have to tell me
it's like it?
If fundamentally it's not required. Very weak read of the mishna משנה.
mishna. Okay, mi b'toch beitah k'mi, mah b'mitah מי בתוך ביתה כמי
מה במטה, mi b'toch beitah k'mi mah b'mitah, so talking about the...
Maybe, but I mean, but why and nevertheless, okay, that's worse in
a way. That's he's right there. Anyway, okay, strange. That's a very
strange read. But what's the debate about? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says: d'keivan d'chatzeir mishtameret l'daatah hi, mitgoreshet דכיון דחצר משתמרת לדעתה היא
מגורשת. d'keivan d'chatzeir mishtameret l'daatah hi, mitgoreshet. So here's explaining why I
would think that you need b'toch בתוך, b'toch, not exactly for a
because the physical presence is needed, obviously not, because we don't need
the physical presence, but you need it that the yard is guarded
sort of under her auspices, you know, sort of under her watch,
and not through somebody else's watch. What does that mean? How would
it be guarded through not mi-daatah מדעתה? mi-daatah? Doesn't mean if you
have a good fence around it, then that is mi-daatah מדעתה, mi-daatah,
she made the fence. So the case of something that she owns
that's protected not mi-daatah מדעתה, mi-daatah, the Gemara's גמרא'ס Gemara's going to
say later, is her slave. If you put it in the hand
of her slave, and her slave is awake, even though her slave
is considered to be her property, in that case the slave is
the one who is fundamentally the watcher of that object. If you
put it in my yard and I've got I've hired a guy
to watch my yard and to guard my yard, nevertheless I'm sort
of like controlling it, it's through me that this thing is being
watched. But presumably an understanding that even if I told my slave
to watch and protect objects that I put on his body, nevertheless
fundamentally he's seen as the primary, I mean it's his body, so
he's seen as the primary person that is watching and controlling that,
and therefore that excludes that case. But in any case other than
that, it's considered mishtameret l'daatah משתמרת לדעתה, mishtameret l'daatah, and it works,
and that's why it works even if she's not physically on the
yard. Now I want to say by the way, well let's take
the next line in the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Very much suggestive this
debate of the two models I put out there. So let's look
at the next line of the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Hachi ka'amar הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, v'hi b'toch she mi-daatah מדעתה. mi-daatah. Hi mitgoreshet
היא
מגורשת, hi mitgoreshet, so she's divorced. Leima לימא. leima. והכי קאמר. V'hachi
ka'amar. ואי פירשו. V'ee peirshu. Okay, מדעתה, m'da'ata, היא מתגרשת. hi mitgereshet.
לימא בהא קמיפלגי. Leima beha kamipalgi. דמר סבר חצר משום יד אתרבאי,
Demar savar chatzer mishum yad itrabai, ומר סבר חצר משום שליחות אתרבאי.
umar savar chatzer mishum shlichus itrabai. Now this is a general debate
in all of שס Shas about how come something works when it
comes into my yard, a normal act of קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
Is it like it's on my person, is it ידה, yada, or
is it that it somehow represents my interests? So the גמרא Gemara
says maybe that's the debate, the classic debate we have in general
about קנין חצר kinyan chatzer is the debate here. It has to
be like my hand, then I have to be standing there. If
it has to just represent my interests, I don't have to stand
there unless it's sufficient that it's משתמרת לדעתה. mishtameret l'da'atah. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. Now, as I've been saying, you
could say that maybe by other קניינים kinyanim it's חצר משום שליח,
chatzer mishum shliach, but by גט get maybe it has to be
חצר משום יד. chatzer mishum yad. You know, again, that emphasis, that
sort of, you know, because it's נתן בידה, natan b'yadah, right, and
it's not a real שליח, shliach, so maybe the whole חידוש chiddush
is that it's considered an extension of her and she has to
be standing on it. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, not
necessarily. דכולי עלמא חצר משום יד אתרבאי. d'chulei alma chatzer mishum yad
itrabai. Everybody could say חצר chatzer is a type of a יד.
yad. מר סבר כידה. mar savar k'yadah. The one holds, okay, that's
a simple application of that principle, like her hand. מה ידה בסמוכה
אף חצר בסמוכה. mah yadah b'sumucha af chatzer b'sumucha. The same way
her hand is right on, she's next to her hand on her
body, she's attached to it, so the חצר chatzer she has to
be like in the חצר chatzer so it's seen as an extension
of her. ואידך, v'idach, the other would say, אם מה ידה בדבוקה
אף חצר בדבוקה. im mah yadah b'dvuka af chatzer b'dvuka. Way, how
far are you going to take this? So maybe we'll say the
hand is like not just, she's not just next to her hand,
she's connected to her hand. So you think she's got to be
connected to her yard? You think you got to like dig a
hole and she has to stand in the hole or something? You
got to glue her onto the yard? I mean, how far are
you going to take this comparison? אלא, ela, so we don't say
it that it's a question about the physical proximity. אלא כידה, ela
k'yadah, it's more of a conceptual idea. מה ידה משתמרת לדעתה, mah
yadah mishtameret l'da'atah, the same way something in my hand is something
that I watch and I protect and so on, so
אף חצר משתמרת לדעתה. af chatzer mishtameret l'da'atah. Anything that is under
my auspices and is protected through me is considered like my hand.
So it's not because it's, we're working with a different model, we
are dealing with the model of יד, yad, but the question is
how literal and physical do you have to be about what constitutes
יד? yad? Physically an extension of me, then I have to be
standing on it. Or not physically, anything that I'm protecting, you know,
the whole idea of יד, yad, right, you know, is a metaphor.
My hand, you know, what's like a פסוק pasuk about that, like,
well, there's ya... the idea like my hand represents like אף ידי
יסדה ארץ af yadi yasdah aretz or something like, well, certainly by
God, אף ידי יסדה ארץ af yadi yasdah aretz or something like,
you know, the idea of hand represents power, control, and so on.
So the idea that it's included in hand means the conceptual idea
of what a hand is. Something under her power, under her control,
that's considered יד. yad. It's not necessarily that the חצר chatzer has
to be some physical extension of her. לאפוקי חצר משתמר שלא לדעתה,
l'afukei chatzer mishtamer shelo l'da'atah, as opposed to something when it's not
לדעתה, l'da'atah, it's under somebody else's control. Like my slave is controlling
it, or certainly if somebody else, you know, my חצר chatzer isn't
משתמר mishtamer at all. Okay, so according to this, it's a way
of being two concepts of what יד yad is. In a very
physical sense, as part of my body, or what's under my control.
Two ways of defining יד yad and that is the debate and
so on. Now it would be interesting to know what, you know,
by גט get we actually rule that you have to be עומדת
בתוך חצרה. omedet b'toch chatzerah. Okay, the actual הלכה halacha is by
גט, get, look at the
רמב"ם. Rambam. Let me just quote this רמב"ם Rambam for a second.
Right, the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens היא עומדת. hi omedet. Hold on,
let me just check this. ה גירושין ב.
he
Gerushin bet.
It's not home, it's not good. What?
Mail to
you and you're not home, it's not good. Mail to you and
you're not home. Yeah, we're going to have a case like after
it's given, can you redefine the act, but yeah. הזורק לאשתו לתוך
חצרה אם הייתה עומדת שם בצד חצרה נתגרשה ואם לאו לא נתגרשה
שם עד שתעמוד בצד חצרה. Hazorek l'ishto l'toch chatzerah im hayta omedet
sham b'tzad chatzerah nitgareshet v'im lav lo nitgarsha sham ad she'ta'amod b'tzad
chatzerah. Okay. ואף על פי שהיא חצר שמשתמרת הגט בתוכה. v'af al
pi she-hi chatzer she-mishtameret haget b'tochah. Okay.
So the רמב"ם Rambam says שחוב הוא לה she-chov hu lah גירושין,
gerushin, ואין חבין לאדם אלא בפניו. v'ein chavin l'adam ela b'fanav. But
it's interesting the way the רמב"ם Rambam frames it. Not because it
has to be יד, yad, but because how can you call it
a שליח, shliach, right, because it's, it's against her, it's not in
her benefit. So why would the חצר chatzer represent her שליח shliach
or as her שליחות? shlichus? So that's the way the רמב"ם Rambam
frames it. The suggestion is, and I'm pretty sure that the רמב"ם
Rambam rules that by other הלכות, halachot, not by
גט, get, יז אבידה י, yud zayin aveidah yud, that you do
not have to be there. But that could be again because it's
more of an issue of, what do you call it,
of שליחות, shlichus, but you, but it's considered to be for somebody's
benefit. Let me just take one second, look at
this. יז אבידה
י.
yud zayin aveidah
yud. משום חצר משום
ידו.
mishum chatzer
mishum yado.
אבל האיש שמצא שחצרו קנה לו משלוחו. aval ha-ish she-matza she-chatzeroh kono
lo mishlucho. Right, so the רמב"ם Rambam says that. But so anyway,
the רמב"ם Rambam has a difference, but it could be that actually
it sounds like the way the רמב"ם Rambam is framing it that
they're both a type of שליחות, shlichus, except one is for somebody's
benefit and one is not somebody's
benefit. Another way of distinguishing is to say by אשה *Isha* it
has to operate on the יד yad, *Yad* model, which actually other
גמרות gemarot *Gemoras* sound like that's very much true and this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* sounds like it is, whereas by קניינים kinyanim, *Kinyanim* it
could operate on the שליח *Shliach* model. And if it's operating on
the יד yad? *Yad* model then the question is how much does
it have to be physically an extension or just seen under somebody's
control. Yes?
So it comes based on this very weird dichotomy. So like let's
say she has a thousand acre estate and you know husband throws
it and puts it right in the middle, it's קונה *Koneh*, you
know she's just guard watching it even though like no one can
see it and no one can go and take it. Then she
but if he gives it right to the guard, the guard says
oh I know this is a very important document, I'm gonna keep
it with me right here. So so that's not good?
Right. Pretty much. That's correct. I mean it doesn't work as שליחות
*Shlichus* and it doesn't work as a יד *Yad*. Yeah. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay. Okay. ההוא
גברא *Hahu Gavra* a man דזרק לה גיטא לדבי דהו *Dezarak Lah
Gitta Lidevei Dehu*. And again this also in my mind always goes
back to the question of is it about קניין kinyan *Kinyan* or
is it about an act of giving. A certain man threw a
גט get. *Get* to his wife. הוי קיימא בחצר *Havah Ka'ima Bechatzer*
and she was in a yard. אזל גיטא נפל בפיסלא *Azal Gitta
Nafal Befisla* and the גט get. *Get* went and it rolled away
and it fell on like a piece of wood. אמר רב Amar
Rav. יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, חזינא *Chazina* we take a look. אי
הוי ארבע אמות arba amot. על ארבע אמות arba amos. *Ei Havei
Arba Amos Al Arba Amos* if that piece of wood is four
אמות amot *Amos* by four אמות amot *Amos*, פלגי רשותא לנפשה *Palgei
Reshusa Lenafshah* it's its own domain and she's not מגורשת megureshet. *Megureshes*.
If she's in her yard?
That's what the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* gonna ask. ואי לא *Vei Lo*
and if not חדא רשותא היא *Chada Reshusa Hi* and it's all
one. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what you talking about? בהיכי
עסקינן *Baheichi Askinan* what's the case? אילימא בחצר דידה *Eilima Bechatzer Didah*
if it's her yard כי הוי ארבע אמות arba amos מאי הוי
*Ki Havei Arba Amos Mai Havei*. Who cares if it's four אמות
amot, *Amos*? It's in her yard. And so in the airspace of
her yard whatever it should work. לא, צריכה דאושלמה מקום *Lo, Tzericha
De'ushlamah Makom* I'm sorry אלא בחצר דידיה *Ela Bechatzer Di'deih* thank you.
It's in his חצר chatzer, *Chatzer*. כי לא הוי ארבע אמות arba
amos מאי הוי *Ki Lo Havei Arba Amos Mai Havei* if it's
not four אמות amot *Amos* why does it work? It's his yard.
So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says no לא צריכה דאושלמה מקום דאושלמה
מקום *Lo Tzericha De'ushlamah Makom De'ushlamah Makom*. It's his yard and he
lent her the space, he says I'm going to throw you a
גט get. *Get* and I'm lending you the space to use for
you to take possession of this גט get *Get*. Now that raises
interesting questions. Does she have to do a קניין kinyan *Kinyan* on
it like you know all the whole discussion before קנתה אשה קנה
בעלה חצר chatzer וידה באים כאחד *Kansah Isha Kanah Ba'alah Chatzer Veyadah
Ba'im Ke'echad* etc. Here you know here it would sound like he
would have to do a קניין kinyan, *Kinyan* on you know she'd
have to do a קניין kinyan. *Kinyan* to take possession of the
place that at least it's her. But that in itself is a
חידוש chiddush *Chiddush* that
a
rented space can be used right? I mean we had that before
you remember by the שכיב מרע *Shechiv Meira*. That presumably was like
lending I mean he could have been giving but it sounded like
he was lending like his closet to be used and so on.
So here we have a lent yard, a rented or a lent
yard could be used even though the woman's basic title to a
yard isn't enough if the husband has a קניין kinyan פירות *Kinyan
Peiros* right? All very interesting what constitutes sufficient ownership of the property
to work. Anyway let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
He lent her, he threw it on the ground and said I'm
lending you the space.
Yeah, but again that's my point if he said it like oh
here use the space that's just verbal that might not be enough.
I mean everything we've been seeing one would think that she had
to do some מעשה קניין kinyan *Ma'aseh Kinyan* on that space to
be used. Okay. דחד מקום מושלי אינש תרי מקומות לא מושלי אינשי
*Dechad Makom Moshli Inish Trei Mekomos Lo Moshli Inshi* that you are
lending her one space. I said this space I'm lending you. You
know and so if there's a piece of wood and that's defined
as a separate space even though it's in the same you know
borders I only said I was lending you one space to use
not two spaces. Very strange.
Lending her the space it falls on.
I understand you could always say. Yeah you could, sure. ולא אמרן
אלא דלא גבוה עשרה *Velo Amran Ela Delo Gavo'ah Asarah*. And all
of this that it's a less than four by four it's okay
it's considered all to be the same space is when it's less
than ten טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* off the ground. וגבוה עשרה *Vegavo'ah Asarah*
but if it's higher than ten טפחים tfachim *Tefachim* off the ground
this piece of wood it fell on a rock or something אף
af. על גב דלא הוי ארבע אמות arba amos *Af Al Gav
Delo Havei Arba Amos* even though it's not four אמות amos *Amos*
that's considered to be its own separate space sort of like we
have things like this by שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* as well right? What's
considered a כרמלית *Karmelis* and a different רשות *Reshus* four אמות amos
*Amos* you know higher than ten טפחים tfachim *Tefachim*. Anyway ולא אמרן
אלא דלית ליה שם לוואי *Velo Amran Ela Deleis Lei Shem Levai*.
And even again if it's less than four אמות amot *Amos* and
within ten טפחים tfachim, *Tefachim* we consider it to be the same
space if it only if it doesn't have its own name. אבל
אית ליה שם לוואי *Aval Is Lei Shem Levai* if it has
another name meaning an accompanying name אף על גב דלא גבוה עשרה
אף על גב דלא הוי ארבע אמות arba amos *Af Al Gav
Delo Gavo'ah Asarah Af Al Gav Delo Havei Arba Amos* it's its
own space anyway. If you sort of say that's like you know
that's like Pooh corner you know that's like whatever you know that's
the Fred rock over there. So even though it's less than four
אמות *Amos* that has its own identity. Alright anyway very strange to
me the biggest issue besides the idea of one place not two
places is you know the idea that rent lending a space can
count and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't spell out what type of
קניין kinyan *Kinyan* you have to do what constitutes enough of an
ownership of that space to be considered you know your יד *Yad*
to work for גיטין gittin, *Gittin*. Okay?
You'd say that by שבת *Shabbos* I don't remember hearing that.
What? שם לוואי *Shem Levai*? No, no.
Like I feel like with like a chair that's someone you know
what I mean?
A chair. Oh, yeah, don't sit on so-and-so's chairs, right, right, that
could be. Yep. Okay. גבוה עשרה אף על גב דלא הוי ארבע
אמות. arba amos I'm sorry, I'm sorry. אפילו היא אמה עם המטה.
Afilu hi ama im ha mita. If he gives it to her
even if he's there with her in the bed, it doesn't work,
which I find so bizarre. Of course, the closer that he's there
with her, the less it's giving it away from him and giving
it to her. Don't understand the אפילו afilu of the משנה. Mishna.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא שנו אלא במיטה שלו. lo shanu ela
be mita shelo. When is it that it doesn't work? If it's
his bed. So even the more, what's the אפילו afilu of the
משנה? Mishna? אבל מיטה שלה מגורשת. Aval mita shela megureshet. Her bed,
she is מגורשת. megureshet. Presumably even if he's there with her in
the bed. Okay, maybe not, maybe so what? It's like he's standing
on her property, right? He's standing together on her property, he drops
it in her yard, doesn't matter that he's there, she's מגורשת. megureshet
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer,
במיטה שלו אינה מגורשת במיטה שלה מגורשת. be mita shelo eina megureshet
be mita shela megureshet. So now the גמרא Gemara says, and here
becomes the whole question, right, about one minute, until now we've been
talking about on her person or on her property, like physical, like
real estate on the ground that she owns, that that's an extension
of her. This, the bed presumably is in his house, right? So
why is that considered to be giving it to her? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
במיטה שלה מגורשת, be mita shela megureshet, why does that work? כלי
של לוקח ברשות מוכר הוא. Kelay shel lokeach birshut mocher hu. It
essentially is, if I'm trying to sell you, you come into my
store and you want to buy some wine, and you take out
your jug and I pour some wine into it. Okay, have you
done a קניין kinyan. because it's now in your jug? So your
jug is in your כלים, kelayim, that's like on your property. Or
do we say, but your property is in my property? So fundamentally
this is still in my space and not in your space. So
how do you define when whose property it's in when it's in
your vessel but your whole vessel is on my property? So the
גמרא Gemara says, well, that's exactly this case. Maybe if you tell
me it works to put it on her bed when it's in
his house, should we infer from this that in general a קניין
kinyan, works if it's somebody's vessel in another person's property? Maybe we
should, but okay, but we know that's an open question. So the
גמרא Gemara says, כלי של לוקח ברשות מוכר, kelay shel lokeach birshut
mocher hu, it's the vessel of the purchaser in the domain of
the seller.
שמע מינה דכלי של לוקח ברשות מוכר קנה לוקח, Shema mina de
kelay shel lokeach birshut mocher kana lokeach, that does it work because
that is considered still fundamentally your property because it's in your vessel?
Okay, okay, maybe we could conclude that, but we know that's an
open question. It says, no, no, no, we can make it a
special case. דגבוה עשרה, De gavoah asara, the bed is more than
10 טפחים tfachim off the ground. So therefore it's not like sort
of like we said before, since it's above the airspace, even though
normally in a house for like שבת purposes, anything in the house
is considered, doesn't matter how high, it's considered to be part of
the רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, but nevertheless, for these purposes, 10 טפחים
tfachim, off the ground is considered to be enough of its own
space that if it's in my vessel, even if it's on your
property, but more than 10 טפחים tfachim. off the ground, it works.
If it rises to a height of 10 טפחים, tfachim, now does
it...
No, no, no, let's say I go ahead and I put, you
know, I put my jug on your counter, and your counter is
more than 10 טפחים off the ground, more than 30 inches. But
it stands on the ground. But ah, so that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. The גמרא Gemara says, ואיכא מקום כרעי, Ve'ika makom karay, so
the same with the legs of the counter.
ואיכא מקום כרעי, Ve'ika makom karay, so how about the place where
the legs are? It's all attached to the ground. מקום כרעי לא
קפיד איניש, Makom karay lo kapid inish, you don't mind that your
wife uses your space for keeping her bed there. So one minute,
so then in the end is the answer so if they don't
mind if it's considered like he lets her use it, which echoes
back the גמרא gemara about borrowing the space, so is it enough
that you're not מקפיד? makpid? Is that enough or is it a
combination? Why do you need more than 10, you could say not
מקפיד makpid is not enough to make it her יד, but maybe
to make it that it's like she has rights here and if
it's in her vessel that works, so then it should be even
less than 10 טפחים, right? And how do you translate this anyway
to a case of when I'm selling you something and you put
your jug down and I pour wine in it? I'm also letting
you put your jug down, maybe there's a difference, there it's only
for a minute, here the bed he allowed, you know, long-term the
bed to be in the space. But anyway, it's a little unclear
how the לא מקפיד lo makpid is needed together with the higher
than 10 טפחים. Anyway, look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says, מקום
כרעי לא קפיד איניש לכל הפחות באשתו makom karay lo kapid inish
le'chol hapachot be'ishto וכן באויר המיטה. ve'chein be'avir hamita. Okay, at least
when it comes to his wife. Okay, other people maybe he would
be more מקפיד. makpid. So again, what we start getting here is
on the one hand intersecting with classic discussions of what constitutes a
קניין, kinyan so looking at that as like the normal world of
קניינים, kinyanim, but at the other hand, some weird special considerations, right,
right, this whole of like, you know, does it verbal שאלה sheila
enough or do you need to actually does she need to physically
take possession of the יד? You're לא מקפיד, lo makpid, more than
10 טפחים, which worked in this case, doesn't work in other cases.
So again, it could be we're all working under the same rubric
of קניינים, kinyanim. but there're just, you know, different factors that factor
in. But again, the question is also how much are we looking
at a different model, a model of an act of giving and
not so much an act of קניין. Okay, so now the גמרא
gemara goes on. לתוך חיקה אותו כלסה מגורשת Le'toch cheika oto kalsa
megureshet and we're going to see here... The same issue. You throw
it into her חיקה, cheika, which could either mean her chest or
bosom or her lap. It's interesting, the same word means two things
in Hebrew. Lap I think fits better, although I or into her
basket. Now her lap should be obvious, that's on her body. Okay,
but the basket, we get back to an idea like the bed.
Where's the basket? Okay, so the גמרא gemara says אמאי, amai, why
does the basket work? כלי של לוקח ברשות מוכר הוא. kli shel
lokeach breshut mocher hu. It's the vessel of the לוקח lokeach in
the domain of the מוכר. mocher. Because if it was on her
yard, you wouldn't need to talk about the basket. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל כגון שהייתה קלתה תלויה בה. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
kegon shehayta kaltah tluyah bah. No, she's got her basket, it actually
is like suspended around her. Yeah, or like actually, yeah, like a
purse or since it's holding. תלויה בה tluyah bah actually sounds even
more than that, like it's like she's got like on a chain
around her neck. I actually, you know, there's a whole discussion about
קלתה kaltah was something that they also had a way of covering
their hair with like some type of a basket thing around their
head. Okay, so that really is considered like an extension of the
body. But yeah, Michael's right, maybe holding on is also an אף.
The גמרא gemara is going to discuss קשורה kshurah in a minute.
וכן אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא כגון שהייתה קלתה תלויה בה.
vechein amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya kegon shehayta kaltah tluyah bah.
וריש לקיש אמר קשורה אף על פי שאינה תלויה. veReish Lakish amar
kshurah af al pi she'einah tluyah. No, if it's tied to her,
even though it's not suspended. Let's say she's got it, it's dragging
on the ground, but it's like, I don't know, some string ties
it to her leg or some bizarre thing like that. Okay, obviously
a third possibility would be you need both קשורה kshurah and תלויה.
tluyah. That would be the case of like suspended around the neck,
right? Michael's example of holding is a case of תלויה tluyah without
קשורה. kshurah. Okay, okay, ורב אדא
בר
אהבה אמר כגון שהייתה קלתה מונחת לה בין ירכותיה.
veRav Adda
bar Ahava amar kegon shehayta kaltah munachat lah bein
yarkoteha. It was between her thighs. She was sitting down. Now, so
what? But if it is like is she holding it off the
ground between her thighs? Then it's a type of a case of
תלויה. tluyah. Is it on the ground? Then why does it work?
So רש"י Rashi says בין ירכותיה, bein yarkoteha, ואף על פי שמונח
בקרקע veaf al pi shemunach bakarka says רש"י, Rashi, אינו מקפיד על
כל מקום מושב אשתו. eino makpid al kol makom moshav ishto. Similar
to the גמרא Gemara? before that you're not מקפיד makpid about where
the bed is. Over there we needed it higher than עשרה טפחים.
asarah tefachim. The guy isn't מקפיד makpid his wife has a right
to sit wherever she wants. Okay, but again it works because it's
in her כלים. keilim. It's just that his domain doesn't, doesn't trump
that because he fundamentally is not מקפיד makpid that she's there. ועד
עכשיו היתה אותו מקום קנוי לה. vead achshav hayta oto makom kanuy
lah. Okay, but of course the phrase of רש"י Rashi קנוי לה
kanuy lah seems to be going even further. You know, that like
but but again, it presumably is not working because it's in her
domain, that's not like the space she's on is her חצר, chatzer
but it's in her, it's in her, it's in her כלי, kli,
and therefore and but it's okay for it to be her כלי
kli that his sense of it being his domain doesn't overpower that.
So the גמרא Gemara, now
continues: רב משרשיא בר רב דימי אמר כגון שהיה בעלה מוכר קלתות.
Rav Mesharshiya bar Rav Dimi amar kegon shehaya ba'alah mocher kaltot. The
husband sold baskets. So? So רש"י Rashi says therefore anywhere there's a
basket in the house, I don't care. What does that have to
do with? It's her basket. So I guess it means that the
house is scattered, you know, the house is filled with baskets. So
what's one more basket? So somehow, you know, that means the sense
that it's his domain there's fundamentally lack of הקפדה, hakpadah, right, then
that's again, what's so funny is why we're framing this as lack
of הקפדה. hakpadah. Why don't we just say in any scenario if
she's in the house and the basket's on the ground, he's implicitly
letting it be there? He's not saying, get your darn basket off
the ground, right? Why do we have to make it like it
seems like that wouldn't be enough? If it's only being allowed there
because it's a special case that he permits it to be there,
fundamentally, like his ownership is established, you know, his presence is established.
Okay, you can put it down, but because I'm giving you permission.
So that's not enough of her establishing a sense of a presence.
But if the default is that she has a right to do
it, she has a right for her bed to be there, she
has a right to sit wherever she wants, you know, it's a
default, not a special case, then that's more that she's established her
presence and it can be in the basket. Okay.
Let's just finish this: רבי יוחנן אמר מקום חיקה קנוי לה מקום
קלתה קנוי לה. Rabbi Yochanan amar makom cheika kanuy lah makom kaltah
kanuy lah. The same way she has the place for her lap
is, she has the right to have wherever her basket is. So
that sounds like that, no, like sort of like the גמרא Gemara.
before about the bed. You don't need it to be a special
case of בין ירכותיה. bein yarkoteha. Fundamentally, the wife has a right
to put down the basket wherever she wants. אמר רבא מאי טעמא
דרבי יוחנן? amar Rava mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan? Why? לפי שאינו מקפיד
לא על מקום חיקה ולא על מקום קלתה. lefi she'eino makpid lo
al makom cheika velo al makom kaltah. Person isn't מקפיד makpid where
his wife wants to sit and where she wants to put down
the basket. So again, as long as it's not, as long as
it's not like a special permission that was granted here, it's an
ongoing allowance, then it can work because it's in her כלים keilim
and his domain does not overpower it. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami
hachi, we taught similarly: זרקו לה לתוך חיקה או לתוך קלתה או
לתוך כל דבר שהוא כקלתה הרי זו מגורשת. zarko lah letoch cheika
o letoch kaltah o letoch kol davar shehu kekaltah harei zu miguyareshet.
Anything that's like her basket. כל דבר שהוא כקלתה לרבויי מאי? kol
davar shehu kekaltah lribuyei mai? What does it include? לרבויי טסקא דאכלה
בה תמרי, lribuyei taska deachla bah tamrei, to include some type of
a basket that you eat dates from. Again, I don't know exactly
what the דחידוש d'chiddush is, maybe that something like that is also...
into her lap and וזקפה vezakfa לתוך letoch חקה cheika או o
לתוך letoch כלתה kaltata או o לתוך letoch כל kol דבר davar
שהוא she'hu ככלתה ke'kaltata הרי harei זו zu מגורשת megureshet. anything that's
like her basket כל kol דבר davar שהוא she'hu ככלתה ke'kaltata למאי
le'mai אתיא atya לטויי le'atuyei תסקא taska דאכלה de'achla בה bah תמרי
tamrei to include some type of a basket that you eat dates
from. Again, I don't know exactly what the חידוש chiddush is, maybe
that something like that is also something she fundamentally has permission. Again,
one wonders like what is, why is it תניא נמי הכא? tanya
nami hacha? How does this support our earlier contention? Unless the point
is to say, no, no, no, it has to be certain types
of things like a basket that she has a right to put
whatever she wants. But other types of things that are her vessels
might not count. That presumably is the תניא נמי הכא. tanya nami
hacha. David, you had a question.
What's the implication of this general framework of these people living together
in this context? In other words, this wife is in this house.
Right, but she's about to get divorced.
No, but I mean, say they're not getting divorced, just the general
living conditions. So I mean, she
is...
Right, your question
is, the sense that she has to get permission to do everything.
Right, exactly, that's the thing. Like, you know, I don't get it.
Like, so during the... here they are they're married, whatever. She wants
to go ahead and she brings home some groceries, right? She's not
allowed to put it down because they're his groceries? If she actually
bought it with some of her own money, she would have to
ask permission to put it down? Like, I'm with you, like I
don't even begin to understand this. Like doesn't, isn't he not מקפיד
makpid on any place that his wife puts anything like in the
house? Like doesn't she implicitly have, you know, that right as an
ongoing thing? Unless the point is in the immediate context of divorce,
but doesn't sound that way either. Then why are we assuming that
he is מקפיד makpid if it's in the immediate context of divorce?
I'm with you, I don't really understand that.
Yes, if they're not מקפיד, makpid, so can an individual kind of
revoke that as specifically retroactive?
Yeah, presumably, I mean, presumably yes. You know, that's why I was
saying before, it's not like she has a real קנין kinyan and
a real right. It's just as a general rule. Like somehow it
seems like if he had to give her special permission, it wouldn't
count. But
if by default he allows it, it's not seen like his presence
like overtakes that it's her space. But I presumably he could be
מקפיד. makpid. That's what it sounds like. All right, very confusing. I
don't know. Like sometimes it's the simple גמרות that are deceptive. Okay,
let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishna. אמר לה,
amar lah, so now we move on to the active giving, well
it is the active giving but not the question of going onto
her person or property but the framing in which it's given. אמר
לה כנסי שטרך זה, amar lah kinsi shetarach zeh, we quoted this
before you might remember or something like this. If he says to
her here, take this... would you mind taking this business document?
And then she opens it up and he says, haha, surprise! Okay.
כנסי שטרך זה kinsi shetarach zeh או שמצאו מאחוריו o shematza'o me'achorav
or she picks it up from behind him. קראה והרי הוא גיטה
kara'ah veharei hu gittah and then she reads it and she realizes
it's a גט. get. אינו גט eino get it's not good עד
שיאמר לה הילך גיטך. ad she'yomar lah hileich gitteich. It has to
be given, and not only does it have to be given, it
has to be given in the context of being a גט.
get, Wait, but he can throw it into her yard.
Yeah, but he has to say הילך גיטך. hileich gitteich.
Or maybe even או בחצר... o bachatzer... Oh, so it has to
be...
where that goes back to the debate of whether she has to
be standing there or not.
So that's a good question. She might not have to hear him
say it, but it might be the difference between being misrepresented as
opposed to for anybody who's there to see it, he's being clear
about what it is. Okay, but that's a good question. I'm going
to touch on some of that in a minute. Okay. נתן בידה
והיא ישנה natan beyada vehi yeshena
let's say he gave it to her and she's asleep. ניעורה קראה
והרי הוא גיטה ne'ora kara'ah veharei hu gittah
and then she wakes up and reads it and behold it's her
גט. get. אינו גט עד שיאמר לה הילך גיטך. eino get ad
she'yomar lah hileich gitteich. It's not good, he has to be told,
so she has to be awake. So Michael raises a good question:
let's say she's awake but she's somewhere else, right? I mean, the
גמרא Gemara before said she could be in צפורי, Tzippori, so presumably
she's not there, right? So somehow there's a difference, at least there
somehow conceptually we say she's in a position to know, anybody who's
there knows, you combine the pieces. But here, right, even though she
was physically present, she was unaware and that's not good. Now, interestingly,
the גמרא Gemara never asks how do you know that this is
true? How do you know that you need to frame it in
the right way? There's a רמב"ם Rambam and תוספות Tosafot come up
with different explanations. תוספות Tosafot says אינו גט עד שיאמר לה. eino
get ad she'yomar lah. Okay, let's actually read this תוספות. Tosafot. רי
היה מצריך לנותן גט לאשתו לומר הילך גיטך Ri hayah matzrich lenoten
get leishto lomar hileich gitteich like
this גמרא Gemara says וגם הרי את מותרת לכל אדם vegam harei
at miteret lechol adam when it was given, to verbally say behold
you are permitted to any man כדמשמע בהמגרש שהיו רגילים לומר גם
כן kedemashma be'Hamgaresh shehayu regilim lomar gam kein ודין vedein
you know, this should be from you, from me to you, a
writ of divorce, והרי את מותרת לכל אדם veharei at miteret lechol
adam and it sounds like that that was not only the text
of the גט get, which it is, but that was verbally stated.
ומיהו קשיא דבנזיקין משמע דאפילו לא אמר כשר umihu kashya debinezikin mashma
de'afilu lo amar kasher גבי מה דאמר ר' יוחנן בן גודגדא נשמע
אמר לעדים ראו גט זה שאני נותן לאשתי gabei mah de'amar Rabbi
Yochanan ben Gudgada nishma amar le'eidim re'u get zeh she'ani noten leishto
you might remember that case. A guy goes to witnesses to say
look at this, see this? It's a גט. get I'm going to
give it to my wife. But I don't want to tell her
גט, get, but you see that it's a גט. get. And then
he goes over and he brings his friend to say, hey hon,
you remember Fred and George? Right, oh by the way, you want
to take this... do you mind taking this letter for me? Okay,
so they know that it's the גט, get. and it's obvious to
them, and she doesn't, and it says there that it's good. And
the גמרא Gemara actually learns it out
from the fact that a גט get. can be given to a
woman who's a שוטה, shota, right? And she doesn't have to be
aware about what the meaning is. ר' יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Gudgada oh no, חרשת chereshet that she by a חרשת, chereshet,
okay, not שוטה shota who's less of a בת דעת. bat da'at.
Okay. Okay, so anyway, so isn't that against this גמרא? Gemara ויש
לומר דהתם נמי אחר כך יגידו לה העדים שהיא מגורשת. V'yeish lomar
d'hasam nami achar kach yagidu lah ha'eidim shehi megureshet. Okay, which sort
of injects a little bit of Micah's issue about not being there.
There maybe you combine the pieces. It's objectively knowable,
which is funny, because it's been misrepresented, which is worse than just
not knowing. But there's objective knowledge, and they maybe will correct it,
so somehow we're able to combine those pieces. Okay, which is still
obviously not a great... I mean, still like that's not... does not
sound great, that situation. אף על פי דאשה מתגרשת בעל כרחה. af
al pi d'ish misgareshas bal korchah. Now he's going to talk about
where we know this from. So first it's resolving with that other
גמרא, Gemara which certainly raises questions that this is not all black
and white. Now where do we know this from? So תוספות Tosfos
says: אף על פי דאשה מתגרשת בעל כרחה, מכל מקום צריך לומר
לה הי גיטך והרי את מותרת לכל אדם שתדע שהיא מגורשת ולא
תהא חוזרת דבעינן שיהא משלחה ואינה חוזרת. af al pi d'ish misgareshas
bal korchah, mikol makom tzarich lomar lah hei giteich v'harei at muteres
l'chol adam sheteida shehi megureshet v'lo tehai chozeres d'bai'inan sheyehei m'shalcha v'eina
chozeres. So תוספות Tosfos says, and this has came up before talking
about a חרשת chereshet and a קטנה ktanah whatever, that it
says ושלחה מביתו והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר. v'shalachah mibeito v'halcha v'haysa l'ish
acher. That she has to understand what this act of divorce means.
So therefore she has to understand that she is divorced. Okay. So
that's her תוספות. Tosfos. It's not just to define it as an
act of giving a גט, get it's that it only works if
the consequences of it are that she understands that she's being divorced.
Which actually one could say that maybe you don't actually have to
have the act and the statement come at the same time. Because
it's not which is... well, yes. Like חצר chatzer. and like the
עדים eidem and like the משנה. Mishnah. Because the משנה Mishnah says
if he gave it to her and said it's a שטר חוב
shtar chov and then later he says it sounds like הי גיטך,
hei giteich, it works to say הי גיטך hei giteich after the
act of giving. Which works fine for תוספות. Tosfos. Now רמב"ם Rambam
comes up with his own דרשה. drashah. Maybe he found it in
the מדרש הלכה, Midrash Halachah, I don't know. But here's what רמב"ם
Rambam says. רמב"ם Rambam says: אמר לעדים ראו גט זה שאני נותן
לה. amar l'eidim reu get zeh she'ani noten lah. This is פרק
א' הלכה י'. Perek Aleph, Halachah Yud. ראו גט get שאני נותן
לה וחזר... sorry, no. ומנין שאינו ניתן לה אלא בתורת גירושין? How
do you know that it's אינה ניתנה לה אלא בתורת גירושין? eina
nitna lah ela b'torat geirushin? It has to be given to her
in the context, you know, framed as a גט. get? שנאמר ספר
כריתות ונתן בידה. Shene'emar sefer kritut v'natan b'yadah. So the act of
the נתינה netinah has to be clear that it's a ספר כריתות.
sefer kritut. Okay.
It's clear, it's defined as a ספר כריתות sefer kritut that he
is giving to her. שיתנו אותה בתורת ספר כריתות. Sheyeiteinu otah b'torat
sefer kritut. It has to be given in that capacity. אבל אם
ניתן לה בתורת שטר חוב או מזוזה אינו גט. Aval im nitan
lah b'torat shtar chov o mezuzah eino get. ואם אמר אחר כך
הוא הי גיטך הרי זה גט. V'im amar achar kach hu hei
giteich harei zeh get. Okay. And then the רמב"ם Rambam speaks about
the עדים eidem and he says the עדים eidem is good because
like תוספות Tosfos says, the עדים eidem will tell
her. שהרי הודיע את העדים שניתן בתורת
גירושין. Sheharei hodia es ha'eidim shenitan b'toras geirushin. Oh, no, תוספות Tosfos
doesn't say the עדים eidem will tell her. He just says the
עדים eidem know. So for the רמב"ם, Rambam, and this is actually
the difference between whether you have to assume the עדים eidem will
tell the woman. For תוספות Tosfos the idea is that she has
to know that she's divorced. So תוספות Tosfos has to say the
עדים eidem will eventually tell the woman. For the רמב"ם, Rambam, he
doesn't say she has to know that she's divorced. He just says
objectively it has to be defined as an act of giving a
גט. get So if I say to you, "Here's a piece of
mail," then I've redefined it as a different act. I've defined it
as... but if I throw it in her yard or I tell
witnesses even if I'm lying to her, there's objective evidence and knowledge
even if she's ignorant of it, right, that it is actually an
act of a גט. get One wonders why it can't work if
she's asleep. That also could objectively be that, but maybe again, maybe
that's a little different, like none of the necessary player is aware
of it. But anyway, but that's different ways of framing what the
issues are. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara גמרא
Gemara, says:
כי אמר לה הי גיטך מאי הוי? ki amar lah hei giteich
mai havei? So what if he says הי גיטך hei giteich afterwards?
הוי ליה טלי גיטך מעל גבי קרקע... Havei lei tli giteich min
agabi karka... Oh, I'm sorry, the גמרא's Gemara first going on the
case where she picks up the גט get, from behind him. So
the גמרא Gemara says why is the problem about picking up the
גט get from behind him only a problem that he didn't tell
her it was a גט? get The bigger problem, he didn't give
it to her. She picked it off the ground. הוי ליה
טלי גיטך מעל גבי קרקע, Havei lei tli giteich mial gabi karka,
it's "pick up your get from the ground." ואמר רבא: V'amar Rava:
טלי גיטך מעל גבי קרקע, tli giteich mial gabi karka, if he
says to her "pick your get off the ground," לא אמר כלום.
lo amar klum. It's not good because he has to give it
to her. She can't be the one to take it. It has
to come directly from him to her, not coming off the ground.
So the גמרא Gemara says אימא ששלפתו מאחוריו. eima sheshaltfo mei'achorav. Okay,
it doesn't mean she picked it off the ground, it means like
he picked it out of his back pocket. So it went directly
from him to her. But the גמרא Gemara says okay, it's direct,
but he wasn't the one who gave it.
שלפתו נמי בעינן ונתן בידה. Shaltfo nami ba'inan v'natan b'yadah. He has
to give it into her hand. She can't be the one to
take it from him. וליכא, V'leika, you don't have it. So it
says: לא צריכא דארקי ליה חרציה. lo tzricha d'arkei leh chartzei. He
basically
like moved over his body, moved over his, you know, his side
or something, ושלפתה, v'shaltfei, and then she took it from him. So
he did the act of giving because he like jutted out his
body, you know, but and then she took it. But I gotta
tell you, it's still a חידוש chiddush to me, like if he
sticks out his hand to her holding the גט get and she
plucks it from the hand, right, that would still sound like he
didn't give it to her, she took it from him. So I'm
not really getting it. You know, I really don't understand how her
taking it suffices if he has to be
the
one... No, no, no, because the normal is that he puts out
his hand and he drops it in her hand. Or at least
he places it, but he's the one doing the action, right? Here
she's taking it out. So to me that's a big חידוש chiddush,
that that's considered an act of
נתינה. netina.
Alright, anyway, yeah, a typical scenario would be both are acting, right?
If I give you something, I extend it to you and you
receive it. Right, I mean we've kind of conceptualized it as though
he's dropping it in her lap or in her hand, but I
don't think that's really a typical way of
I mean right I mean the משנה Mishnah sort of זרק לה,
zarok lah, it sort of has him very active, right? But you're
right, I mean I guess if it's somehow that they're both doing
it at the same time but this is like he extends and
she takes it. Right, that totally seems like she's the primary right?
I mean that's more akin to a typical act of me giving
you something.
I guess so.
Like what's the difference between here have this apple and then you
take the apple? Right.
Right. Okay, so I get it, but to me that's a חידוש,
chiddush right? That that would be considered an act of נתן בידה.
natan beyada. So I mean I haven't had a chance to look,
but it would be interesting to see how this gets developed,
clarified by the פוסקים. poskim. Okay, תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi
we taught similarly. I mean when they actually give a גט get
you should see how crazy מקפיד makpid they are, like you know
she has to hold her hand like this, she can't move whatever,
like anyway, okay. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami hachi. אמר לה Amar
lah if he says to her כנסי שטר חוב זה kinsi shtar
chov zeh or ששלפתו מאחוריו she-shalafto me-achorav
so here it makes it just clear it doesn't answer the problem
that he has to be active but it just says that she
didn't pick it off the ground, she took it out of his
back pocket. כרצונך והרי הוא גיטך, Kirtzonach ve-harei hu gittech, אינו גט
עד שיאמר לה הרי זה גיטך, eino get ad she-yomar lah harei
zeh gittech, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. It's not good until he says
this is your get. Now רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar omer, now what is a חידוש chiddush of רבי Rabbi
is once we established that it has to be done as a
גט, get, the חידוש chiddush. is that he could say that after
she took it, right? So you could say after she took it,
if it wasn't good then how does it become good now? It's
a little funny that you combine the statement later with the act
of giving and make it all a good package, right? So okay,
that's what רבי Rabbi says but רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar disagrees. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר לעולם אינו גט עד
שיטלנה הימנה ויחזור ויתננה לה ויאמר לה הרי זה גיטך. Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar omer le-olam eino get ad she-yitlena heimena ve-yachzor ve-yitnena lah
ve-yomar lah harei zeh gittech. No, he has to take it back
and give it again and give it the right way. Okay, נתנו
בידה והיא ישנה natno beyada ve-hi yeshena he put it in her
hand she was
asleep, ניעורה והרי הוא גיטך אינו גט עד שיאמר לה הרי זה
גיטך, ne'ora ve-harei hu gittech eino get ad she-yomar lah harei zeh
gittech, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. He has now to tell her it's
a get but that's okay, he doesn't have to give it again.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר עד שיטלנו הימנה ויחזור ויתננו לה ויאמר
לה הרי זה גיטך.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer ad
she-yitlenu heimena ve-yachzor ve-yitnenu lah ve-yomar lah harei zeh gittech. Same debate.
He says no, you have to give it again. וצריכא, u-tzricha, you
need both cases. דאי איתמר בהך קמייתא, de-i itamar be-hach kamayta, if
you said in the case where she thinks it's just like a
business
document, בהיא קאמר רבי, be-hi ka'amar Rabbi,
that's when רבי Rabbi says it's enough to say afterwards משום דבת
גירושין היא, mishum de-bat gerushin hi, because when it was first given
to her she could have been divorced, she was at least conscious,
she was fit to be divorced. אבל נתנו בידה והיא ישנה, aval
natno beyada ve-hi yeshena, but she was asleep דלאו בת גירושין היא,
de-lav bat gerushin hi, that she's not aware of what's going on
at that moment, there's no way she could be divorced at that
moment. אימא מודה ליה לרבי שמעון בן אלעזר, eima modeh leh le-Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, maybe he would agree with רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that you have to re-give it. ואי איתמר
בהא, ve-i itamar be-ha, if we just had the case of her
being asleep, בהא קאמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, be-ha ka'amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar, that's where רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says you have to redo it because she was asleep. אבל בהא,
aval be-ha, when she was awake and it was given as a
שטר חוב, shtar chov, אימא מודה ליה לרבי, eima modeh leh le-Rabbi,
maybe he'd agree to רבי. Rabbi. צריכא, tzricha, you need both cases.
And this makes a lot of sense because again if you say
that the act of giving has to be framed in a particular
way, like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar question is
a good one, how do you combine the later statement with an
earlier act to reframe the act? So if she was conscious the
whole time and you said here's the get and then you said
haha I mean here's your שטר חוב shtar chov haha it's a
get, okay, it's a get, you know and you didn't say ha,
you said here's your get, you know, you said here's your שטר
חוב shtar chov and she opened it and then you said here's
your get, you could sort of see that as a continuous process,
she was conscious, you were engaged in an interaction the whole time
and what you said later defines the whole process even the earlier
stage of the process. Whereas if she was asleep, right, it's a
lot harder to see how when you told her something six hours
later when she woke up that redefines the act you did when
she was asleep. It's very strange that the later statement can redefine
the earlier act especially for רמב"ם Rambam that the emphasis is on
defining the act. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר
רב אמר רבא Amar Rav, Amar Rava says Rava: כתב לה גט
ונתנו ביד עבדה. katav lah get u-netano be-yad avda. Now we're going
to clarify this idea of חצר המשתמרת לדעתו. chatzer ha-mishtameret le-da'ato. If
you wrote a גט get and put it into the hand of
her
slave. ישן ומשמרתו הרי זה גט. yashen u-mesharmato harei zeh get. If
the slave is asleep, it works. נעור אינו גט. ne'or eino get.
If the slave is awake it doesn't work, which is bizarre, we
would think it's better he's awake, he's watching it. But no, that's
the whole problem. דהוי ליה חצר המשתמרת שלא לדעתה. de-havei leh chatzer
ha-mishtameret she-lo le-da'atah. If the slave is awake, the slave is fundamentally
the one in control of the גט get and not her. It's
a חצר chatzer that is watched. not under her direct control. So
says מר Mar says ישן ומשמרו הרי זה גט. yashen umishamro harei
zeh get. One minute, but why does it work when he's asleep?
אמאי? amai? Why is that good? חצר מהלכת היא. chatzer mehalechet hee.
It's a walking חצר. chatzer. We have a principle that a חצר
chatzer only works if it's stationary.
This is an עבד eved or property, but it's a moving חצר.
chatzer. By the way, it's strange, right? Because we actually said that
a
כלב kelev works. כלים keilim don't move. They can be moved by
an external force, but they don't move. So putting it into my
vessel works, that's my property. But putting it onto my slave, why
should that work? That's a חצר that moves on its own.
וחצר מהלכת לא קנה. v'chatzer mehalechet lo kanah. וכי תימא ישן שאני?
v'chi teima yashen shani? Ah, but he's asleep. That maybe helps for
two ways. Number one is it doesn't make it that he's watching
it rather than her and right now he's not moving. So the
גמרא Gemara says: No. ואמר רבא כל שאילו מהלך לא קנה עומד
ויושב לא קנה. v'amar Rava kol she'ilu mehalach lo kanah omed v'yoshev
lo kanah. Anything
that would not work if the slave is walking would not work
if the slave is sitting. Now still, like the earlier גמרא, Gemara
you could say there's a difference between being sitting and being asleep.
Being sitting is because I'm choosing to sit. Being asleep is I'm
in a state where I am not mobile.
But anyway, the גמרא gemara thinks that you can't have a חצר
מהלכת chatzer mehalechet and even if the guy is asleep, it's not
good because he could wake up at any time. So why does
it work? So the גמרא gemara says: והילכתא בכפות. v'hilchata b'chafut. We're
talking about the slave is bound. So he's bound, his legs are
bound, so he can't walk even if he wanted to. So he's
bound and he's asleep, and therefore it works. It's משמרת לדעתה. mishameret
l'da'atah. It's משמרת לדעתה, mishameret l'da'atah, it's not under the control of
the slave and the slave can't walk, so it's not a חצר
מהלכת. chatzer mehalechet. Again, interesting, especially given the earlier גמרא gemara about
being asleep. You could have distinguished between being asleep and just choosing
to sit. Anyway, that ties up the גמרא gemara before about חצר.
Yes, moving back to now this issue about domain and whose domain
it's in. Yes, go ahead.
What do you think percentage of people were literate in those days?
And
she has to
read it, reading it. Good question. I don't know. I think the
number of people that could actually write was probably much less. But
literate?
I don't know. The sense one tends to get is that people
were pretty literate, at least in the Jewish community. I don't know
if there's been a discussion about that. She doesn't have to. Here
it's like even if she reads it and becomes aware, it's not
good unless he
says... All right, let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
הייתה עומדת ברשות הרבים. haita omedet birshut harabbim. Now, that was if
she was in her yard or we even spoke about him lending
space to her or her vessels in his yard. Let's say they're
in the public domain. No vessels, no nothing, they're just there in
the middle of Broadway. וזרקו לה v'zarko lah and he throws it
to her. קרוב לה מגורשת karov lah megureshet if it's closer to
her, she's divorced. קרוב לו אינה מגורשת karov lo eina megureshet if
it's closer to him, she's not divorced. מחצה על מחצה מגורשת ואינה
מגורשת mechetza al mechetza megureshet v'eina megureshet if it's smack in the
middle, she's doubtfully divorced. וכן לעניין קידושין v'chen l'inyan Kiddushin the same
thing is true about קידושין Kiddushin if he threw her a ring,
was it closer to her or closer to him? וכן לעניין חוב
v'chen l'inyan chov and by a debt. Here's the hundred dollars I
owe you, catch. So by the debt, the relevance: אמר לו בעל
חוב amar lo ba'al chov it says, the creditor said: זרוק לי
חובי zerok li chovi throw me the money you owe me. וזרקו
לו v'zarko lo and threw it to him. קרוב למלווה זכה מלווה
karov l'malveh zachah malveh if it was closer to the creditor, he
has his debt paid back and if the money gets lost, that's
his property now. קרוב ללווה הלווה חייב karov l'loveh haloveh chayav if
it was closer to the borrower, the borrower's liable, it still hasn't
been paid back and the borrower has to make sure the debt
is paid. מחצה על מחצה שניהם יחלוקו mechetza al mechetza shneihem yachloku
if it's exactly in the middle
and then let's say it's smack in the middle and then it
got lost, so then the debtor has to pay half the debt.
We don't know. It's sort of like מגורשת. meguresshet. Now, on the
one hand, this would seem to be a great evidence that you
don't need a normal קניין because since when have we heard of
a קניין called it's near to me than to you? In the
middle of the street, it's near to me, since you can't take
possession of something. I want to sell you, I don't know whatever,
my basketball. Here, catch, and I throw it with you and it
lands nearer you or in the middle of a basketball court, right?
What type of a קניין is that? You have to do הגבהה,
hagbahah, you have to do משיכה. meshichah. Who cares that it's nearer
to you? So that would seem to indicate again that this isn't
a normal קניין. It's giving it and somehow because it went away
from my control and further away from me and closer to you,
it's like I gave it to you. The only thing is, though,
that the משנה Mishnah later mentions that it works by קידושין Kiddushin
and it works by חוב. chov. And if it works by קידושין
Kiddushin and it works by חוב, chov, that sounds like it does
work in general by קניינים. kinyanim. But that's bizarre, right? Because we
never heard of that idea of a קניין, something being closer to
me than closer to you. So let's see what the גמרא gemara,
now does with this question. Very strange and provocative משנה. Mishnah. So
the גמרא Gemara says the following: היכי דמי קרוב לה והיכי דמי
קרוב לו? heichi dami karov lah v'heichi dami karov lo? Maybe we're
going to get to the bottom of it by defining terms. What
do you mean nearer to her and nearer to him? It could
just mean literal, but again, that would raise all the questions I
just put out there. What type of a קניין is that? So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב. Amar Rav: אמר Amar, רב: Rav
ארבע אמות שלה זהו קרוב לה, Arba amos shelah zehu karov lah,
ארבע אמות שלו זהו קרוב לו. Arba amos shelo zehu karov lo.
No, קרוב לה karov lah means within her ארבע אמות. arba amos
And what you have to understand is that חז״ל Chazal created a
קנין kinyan of ארבע אמות. arba amos. Okay, that something within my
ארבע אמות arba amos is like, you know, my ארבע אמות arba
amos is like six feet, whatever, it's like, you know, ארבע אמות
arba amos is like when I carry something four אמות in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, I've taken it out of its space. So ארבע
אמות arba amos, is like the immediate environs of something. So something
within ארבע אמות arba amot is like under my control. So actually
חז״ל Chazal created a קנין kinyan if you put something in my
ארבע אמות arba amot. even in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, although there's
some question maybe it has to be a side street. Anyway, that
works. So that's what רב Rav is saying is going on here.
We are talking about a classic קנין. kinyan. The classic קנין kinyan
known as ארבע אמות. arba amot. So within her ארבע אמות arba
amot it works, within his ארבע אמות arba amot it does not
work. Now what רב Rav, doesn't discuss, but I'll spell out for
you is, let's say they're more than eight אמות apart and it
falls between the two. So that also obviously would not work because
it has to get into her control in order to work. So
basically for רב, it has to be in her ארבע אמות arba
amot and that's the קנין kinyan that we're talking about. Now, what's
the מחצה למחצה? mekhtza l'mekhtza? היכי
דמי מחצה למחצה? Heichi dami mekhtza l'mekhtza? What's half and half? אמר
רבי שמואל בר אבדיגון בשניהם עומדים בארבע אמות. Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Avtigon b'shneihem omdim b'arba amot. Basically, they are they're overlapping. The case
is if his ארבע אמות, arba amot, if she's here, right, it's
been a while since I drew pictures, okay, and he's here, you
like the dress? Okay, so if it's here, it's מחצה למחצה. mekhtza
l'mekhtza. It's not literally מחצה למחצה, mekhtza l'mekhtza, but it's in a
space that is both her ארבע אמות arba amot and his ארבע
אמות. arba amot And that's why it's a ספק safek whether she's
מגורשת. meguresshet, Okay.
What? Exactly, it's a Venn diagram. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ולחזי היי מינייהו קדים? V'leikhzi hai minaihu kadim? One minute, who got
to the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim first? First person there claims their
stake. So if I was there first and you came later, you
entered into my space, your ארבע אמות. arba amot And the same
would be the reverse. So that's interesting. So the גמרא gemara says
וכי תימא דאתו תרוייהו בהדי הדדי ואי אפשר לצמצם. V'khi teima d'asu
tarvaihu bahadi hadadi v'ee efshar l'tzamtzem. They showed up at exactly the
same time, but we can never be exact, nothing happens at the
exact time. So, but the גמרא so okay, so it says but
maybe we still have a doubt, so we have a doubt, so
we don't know whose ארבע אמות arba amot. it is. Yes, but
then it's not so interesting. Then the reason we don't know whose
ארבע אמות arba amot. it is is just because we don't have
sufficient facts. If we had the sufficient facts and we knew who
showed up first, we'd know whose ארבע אמות it was. Whereas this
case is more interesting. This case is not just we don't have
sufficient facts, this is a case where objectively it's in a contested
space. Right? So there's one way of saying it's objectively contested as
opposed to saying, oh no, it's one of their ארבע אמות, it's
just the guy who showed up first, we just don't know who
it is. So then it's really just a question about not knowing
the facts. Anyway, so what the גמרא says is אלא אמר רב
כהנא הכא בשמונה אמות מצומצמות עסקינן. Ella amar Rav Kahana hakha b'shmoneh
amot metzumtzamot askinan. We're talking about that there are exactly eight אמות,
גט יוצא מארבע אמות שלה לארבע אמות שלו. get yotzei m'arba amot
shelah l'arba amot shelo. So the case is
that her ארבע אמות goes like this and his ארבע אמות goes
like this and they're exactly eight אמות apart. Okay? And the גט
get goes here. Okay?
You like how quickly I did that?
Okay. Psyche. Okay. Anyway, alright, so I have hidden
talents. Okay. והא אגד גביה? V'ha agid gabei? One minute, says the
גמרא, why is it a ספק? safek? If part of the גט
get, is still in his domain, right, then he still it's like
his hands are still on it, right? So if she has her
hands on half of it and he has his hands on the
other half, she's ודאי vadai not מגורשת, megureshet he's still holding onto
it. So what's the
ספק? safek? אלא רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו, Ella Rabbah v'Rav Yosef
d'amri tarvaihu, they say הכא בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן, hakha b'shnei kitei
edim askinan, אחת אומרת קרוב לה ואחת אומרת קרוב לו. akhas omeret
karov lah v'akhas omeret karov lo. Going back to the thing we
avoided before, that it is just a question of facts. There's different
testimony, two witnesses say we saw it and it landed closer to
her and two witnesses say we saw it and it landed closer
to him and they said okay let's do the instant replay because
the refs are debating. Anyway, so it's basically it's just a question
of ספק, safek, we don't know all the
facts. Fine. That's one approach. Anyway, two and two. I mean, if
it was one and one, yeah, that raise other questions.
But does he still have to release it in his hand when
he's giving it to her or does he have to drop it?
No, he does drop it, he threw it.
I'm saying in general.
In general, yeah, he has to release it, yeah, exactly, mhm. If
he's still holding on, it's not good. Anyway, so this basic idea
though is we're not reading the משנה mishna literally. קרוב לו karov
lo and קרוב לה karov lah means in her ארבע אמות because
we need it to be a classic קנין. kinyan. And a classic
קנין kinyan is within somebody's ארבע אמות. Now though we have רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who gives a more פשט pshat read of this
משנה. mishna. רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, although it's a bigger חידוש. chiddush
רבי יוחנן אומר קרוב לה שנינו. Rabbi Yochanan omer karov lah shaninu.
No, next to her, that's literal. אפילו מאה אמה, afillu me'ah amah,
even if No, next to her. That's literal. אפילו מאה אמה, afilu
meah amah, even if it's a hundred אמות away from her, but
if it's closer to her than to him, that's closer to her.
וקרוב לו שנינו, v'korov lo shaninu, closer to him, אפילו מאה אמה
afilu meah amah even a hundred אמה amah away. So היכי דמי?
heichi dami? It's a hundred אמות away from her, but if it's
closer to her than to him, that's closer to her. וקרוב לו
שנינו, v'korov lo shaninu, closer to him, אפילו מאה אמה afilu meah
amah even a hundred אמה amah away. So היכי דמי? heichi dami?
So meaning, yeah, just means whoever it's closer to, it doesn't have
to be within your ד' אמות. arba amos. So the גמרא says,
היכי דמי מחצה על מחצה heichi dami machtsa al machtsa according to
this? So we could, אמר רב המנונא בר אבא לדידי מפורשא לי
מיניה דרבי יוחנן, Amar Rav Himnuna bar Abba lididi meparsha li minei
d'Rebbe Yochanan, it's explained to me from רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, היא
יכולה לשומרו והוא אינו יכול לשומרו. hi yechola l'shomro v'hu einu yachol
l'shomro. זהו קרוב לו. Zehu korov lo. Now we're clarifying a little
bit. Even though he says it's literal, who's it nearer to and
it's not ד' אמות, arba amos, it's still a little bit conceptual.
What it really means is, who can control it? Who can protect
it? Okay, so if he is able to protect it and she
can't, then it doesn't matter physically where it is, like you don't
just take out a ruler, you know, it's considered under his
control. That's קרוב לו. korov lo. היא יכולה לשומרו והוא אינו יכול
לשומרו, hi yechola l'shomro v'hu einu yachol l'shomro, if it's near enough
to her, wherever it's situated in a place that she has the
ability to access and control it and he does not, no matter
how distant it is, זהו קרוב לה, zehu korov lah, that's near
to her. שניהם יכולין לשומרו, shneihem yecholin l'shomro, if they both equally
can access it and protect it, or
שניהם אינן יכולין shneihem einan yecholin or they both neither can, זהו
מחצה על מחצה, zehu machtsa al machtsa, that's half and half. Okay,
so what do you see though by רבי יוחנן? Rebbe Yochanan? You
see for רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan that you don't need to be
in the ד' אמות. arba amos. As long as she can protect
it and he can't, it works as a גט, which is a
big חידוש because that doesn't work in normal קניינים. kinyanim So again,
that would really point to that there's a different thing that defines
the giving of a גט than a normal קנין. kinyan. And now
the גמרא says, אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבי יוחנן משמיה דרבי יונתן הכי.
amru rabbanan kammei d'Rebbe Yochanan mishmei d'Rebbe Yonatan hachi. So the רבנן
rabbanan said to רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, you know, your read in
the משנה mishna that it's about literally קרוב לה korov lah and
קרוב לו, korov lo, who can protect it, it's not a ד'
אמות arba amos idea, רבי יונתן Rebbe Yonatan says that. רבי יונתן
Rebbe Yonatan back in בבל Bavel says that as well. אמר, so
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said, 'Wow, יודעין חברינו בבבלאי לפרשי כי האי
טעמא!' yodin chavran b'vavlayi l'forushei ki hai ta'ama! Wow, look at that.
Our Babylonian colleagues know how to give a good פשט pshat to
a משנה. mishna.
Like I, you know, like basically which reflects the idea that in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, look in general this debate, in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael they tend to be a more literal read, a closer
read to the text, to the original text of the sources, where
in בבל Bavel they're more free explaining things in ways that are
not always don't have as much sort of literal fidelity, textual fidelity
to the sources. So רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan is like impressed that
they came up with a good פשט pshat in the משנה mishna
presumably that was closer to the פשט pshat of the משנה. mishna.
Even in בבל Bavel there was somebody who was able to figure
that out. Okay. תניא נמי הכי ודמי לי, Tanya nami hachi v'dimi
li, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbe Eliezer omer, כל שהוא קרוב לה מלו,
kol shehu korov lah mi lo, if it's closer to her than
to him, ובא כלב ונטלו, uba kelev v'natlo, and a dog came
and ate it, אינה מגורשת. einah megureshet. טאקי, Taki, it's not good.
So the גמרא says, what do you mean? אינה מגורשת? einah megureshet?
Just because a dog took it, it's not good? וכי חזיה לה
ומינטרא לה? vechi chazya lah v'mintra lah? Does he have to watch
it her whole life? אלא הכי קאמר, Ella hachi ka'amar, this is
what it means. כל שהוא קרוב לה מלו, kol shehu korov lah
mi lo, if it's closer to her than to him, and how
is that defined? Even though physically it's closer to her than to
him, ואם בא כלב ונטלו והוא יכול לשומרו והיא אינה יכולה לשומרו,
v'im ba kelev v'natlo v'hu yachol l'shomro v'hi einah yachola l'shomro, but
if it was physically closer to her than to him, but if
a dog were to come, he could stop the dog and she
couldn't. רש״י Rashi says, maybe there's a big boulder or a river
between her and it. So it doesn't matter physical distance. If he's
in a position to stop the dog and she's not, אינה מגורשת,
einah megureshet, it's not good. Because the point is not physically who
it's closer to. Nobody says to read the משנה mishna that literal.
Even רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan who says it's not about ד' אמות,
arba amos, says it's about who's in a position to guard it
and protect it. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav
Yehuda, so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, he has
a at to the all this thing, שמואל Shmuel said to רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שיננא, shinana, sharp one, כדי שתשוח ותטלנו. kdei shetishoch
v'titlennu. The הלכה halakha actually is, not, it's not enough that she
can protect it, maybe not even enough that it has to be
in her ד' אמות, arba amos, or maybe this is a definition
of ד' אמות, arba amos, it has to be close enough to
her that she can bend down and pick it up. So he
does not, he's being very careful, you know, גיטין, gittin. it's her
whole status, is she מגורשת or not? We're not going to play
around. It has to be really close to her. So close that
she could bend down and pick it up. And even that, ואת
לא תעביד עובדא עד דמטי גיטא לידה, v'at lo ta'avid uvda ad
d'mati gita l'yada, and even that case, you shouldn't rule on to
say she's allowed until the גט actually goes straight into her hand.
So this is expressing, you know, this idea of let's be extra
מחמיר machmir by גיטין. gittin Of course being extra מחמיר machmir by
גיטין gittin also means, you know, keeping the woman bound, you know,
in cases where she should be divorced. Okay. אמר ליה מר בר
אמי לרב אשי, Amar lei Mar bar Ammi l'Rav Ashi, הוה עובדא
הכי, hava uvda hachi, there was a case like this, it was
thrown next to her, maybe she could even bend down and pick
it up, ואצריכוה חליצה v'atzrichua chalitza and they demanded that she do
a חליצה chalitza because it never actually got directly into her hand.
So one even wonders according to this, what do we say? Do
we say pick it up and re-give it? Is it enough that
she actually bends down and picks it up? You know, but now
we come from going all the way to it could be מאה
אמה meah amah away and she could protect it, to okay at
least within ד' אמות, arba amos, that's פשט pshat of the משנה,
mishna, to say that in practice she actually has to get it
directly. onto her person, onto her body. And take a look at
תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות Tosfos at least limits this a little bit. תוספות
Tosfos says, and we'll end with this, דלא תהוי עובדא דאדם עד
דמטי גיטא לידה, delo tehei uvda de'adam ad demati gitta liyada, says
תוספות, Tosfos, והיינו דוקא ברשות הרבים. vehaynu davka bireshus harabim. Okay, that
would be if the public domain, then you really don't have a
real presence in the public domain. אבל בחצר, aval bechatzer, if you
threw it into her yard, אין צריך שיגיע לידה. ein tzarich sheyagia
liyada. Then obviously it doesn't have to get onto her person, because
אע"ג דזמנין דפתיח ודסגיר, af al gav dezamnin depasiach vedasgir, that is
as long as she locks the door, whatever. And then he says
the ערוך Aruch seems to be מחמיר machmir even in a case
of the yard, but then תוספות Tosfos rejects that. But if so,
if it's in her yard, then it doesn't have to be on
her person. But if it's in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, we wind
up effectively פוסק-נינג paskening against this משנה. mishna. So on the one
hand this משנה mishna is radical in the idea that giving a
גט does not need to be a normal act of a קנין,
kinyan, it could be according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan a hundred
אמות away from her, but if she's in a position to protect
it and he's not, that's considered for גיטין purposes that he gave
it to her. The act of giving doesn't have to fit into
a box of a normal קנין. kinyan. Whereas רבא Rava read it
as being within the ארבע אמות. The conclusion of the גמרא is
very מחמיר, machmir, needs it to come to her directly. What we're
going to look at tomorrow is the end of the משנה mishna
that says the same הלכה halacha is true by קידושין kiddushin and
a חוב. chov. Because if this is a special הלכה halacha by
גט, how could the משנה mishna at the end say that it
works by קידושין kiddushin and a חוב chov if normal קניינים don't
work this way? So we'll see about that tomorrow.